Luigi R. Viggiano

Software Engineer

Personal & Contact Information

Name: Luigi Rocco Viggiano

Nationality: Italian Year of birth: 1977

Currently living in: Torino, Italy E-mail: luigi.viggiano@gmail.com

Telegram: @aeonbits



Availability

Available for remote working, free lance or permanent positions, we can discuss about relocation.

Summary

I work as software consultant, developer and architect since 1998. I use Java since 2000.

I have strong experience in the Java platform and most of the related technologies, and good knowledge of unix based systems. I am a fast learner so I can quickly cover new technologies that a job assignment may need. I have been working productively in complex projects and in several industries including telecommunications, banking, government and software engineering.

Objective

I am looking for engaging projects where I can contribute with my experience and ideas and improve my skills. I like lean practices and quality software so I would like to work in an agile team with great engineers, generous and innovative people. I am interested in permanent positions as well as freelance contracts. Recently I developed interest in bitcoin and blockchain technologies.

Main Skills

- System architectures, SOA, OOP/OOA, mobile solutions, enterprise application integration.
- Extensive experience in creating quality web applications and components that promote reuse.
- · Agile software development and robust engineering practices.
- Tasks and time management practices.
- 17+ years of professional experience.

Spoken Languages

· English: full professional proficiency.

Italian: mother tongue.

German: elementary proficiency.

Technical Skills

Languages: J2SE (Java), J2EE (JSP, Servlets, EJB, JDBC, XML), HTML, XML, JavaScript, SQL.

Development Practices: OOP, Design Patterns, Agile Development (XP, SCRUM), Test Driven Development.

Application Servers: Tomcat, JBoss, WebLogic, Jetty, WebSphere, Sun ONE Studio.

Frameworks: Struts/Webwork, GWT, JUnit, Mockito, Spring IOC, Hibernate, Velocity, XDoclet, Ajax.

Tools: Ant, Maven 2, Hudson.

Source Code Management: GIT (Fast Version Control System), Subversion, CVS, SourceSafe.

Databases: Oracle, MySQL, PosgreSQL, FirebirdSQL (Interbase), Microsoft SQL Server.

IDE: IntelliJ IDEA, Eclipse, JBuilder.

Operating Systems: Linux/Unix (bash and tools), Apple OSX, Windows. **Project Management Tools**: Trac, TeamForge, RedMine, HP Quality Center.

Office Automation: OpenOffice.org, Microsoft Office, iWork.

Professional Certifications

- SCBCD: Sun Certified Business Component Developer (EJB) for J2EE 1.3
- SCEA (Part 1): Sun Certified Enterprise Architect for J2EE
- SCPJ1.4: Sun Certified Programmer for Java 2 Platform 1.4 (JDK 1.4)
- SCWCD: Sun Certified Web Component Developer for Java 2 Platform, Enterprise Edition (J2EE)
- SCPJ: Sun Certified Programmer for Java 2 Platform 1.2 (JDK 1.2)

Professional Experience

Software Engineer at Tierra S.p.A. - Leinì (Torino), Italy

June 2014 – June 2015 (1 year)

Working as server side software engineer on a telematics system used in building and agricolture industry for Case - New Holland (CNH). I have been in charge of implementing communication and reporting services between virtual display terminals installed in tractors and building machines using rest APIs.

Software Consultant at UBS Wealth Management - Zurich, Switzerland

June 2010 - March 2012 (1 year 10 months)

I am working in the Equity Investment division of UBS. I'm doing production support on legacy equity booking applications and software development of the new equity platform based on Tibco Enterprise Message Service named "NEDS". I am responsible to keep the software running, implement systems integration, manage the releases and deployments. I started the introduction of agile practices in the team: standup meeting, test driven development, small releases, continuous integration with test coverage and static code analysis (Hudson).

Software Consultant at Vodafone Global - Düsseldorf, Germany

December 2009 – February 2010 (2 months)

I have been providing software consultancy to Vodafone, the scope of the project was to evaluate the migration from Subversion to GIT version control management. I prepared server installations, case studies, documentation, planning, and training to developers on projects introducing the very latest technologies in the source control management. Vodafone has successfully adopted GIT as replacement for Subversion.

June 2009 - October 2009 (5 months)

Technical support for Vodafone MyWeb: http://myweb.vodafone.com/

My duties include: production issues analysis, providing bug fixes, assist OpCos during and after the deployment.

March 2008 - May 2009 (1 year 3 months)

I was working mainly on system integration and internals of a service oriented software platform, offering programming APIs to Vodafone customers to implement applications that can be developed by users and partners, like the Apple Store and the android shop. Now this project has been disclosed and it is known as Vodafone 360: see http://info.vodafone360.com

My assignments included integrating services of companies acquired by Vodafone (http://www.zyb.com) and other partners, architecture definition and development of some 'pillars' of systems available as remote API application services (mainly persistence, security, contact synchronisation).

March 2007 - March 2008 (1 year 1 month)

Java developer in the Vodafone Live! Core Stack team. OpCo support during deliveries, solving bugs, integration and scalability/reliability issues. My assignments included being Google Search Integration Lead for

"Vodafone Live! Core stack", maintenance and improvements on administration tools and adding new features to the mobile portal, and being "application expert" of the platform that is currently serving (and selling to) all Vodafone customers in several countries.

Founder & Coordinator at JUG Torino - Torino, Italy

April 2002 - Current (8 years)

Java User Group Torino is one of the top 25 user group in the world. It's a non-profit organisation born to share experiences, information and to organise activities in order to study and divulgate Java technology, especially in Turin (Italy).

Software Consultant at CSP - Torino, Italy

CSP is a consultancy firm with offices in Torino, Milano (Italy) and Lugano (Switzerland), see: http://www.cspnet.it May 2006 - March 2007 (1 year)

Client: CSI Piemonte. Projects "Piano Lavori Regione, Gestione Piano Lavori, Trattamento Economico Accessorio". Development on applications for public administration and employee payments.

System Developer at Fluidtime Data Services GmbH - Torino, Italy

May 2006 - May 2006 (1 month)

Developer on a digital content provisioning system for cell phones (ringtones, wallpapers, mms, etc.). In this system, you can browse and get the right content for the specific brand and model of your cell phone.

Software Consultant at HP - Torino, Milano, Italy

March 2004 - April 2006 (2 years 2 months)

HP Italy (Torino), on "StarPay" product. Architecture definition, development and customisation of StarPay system. StarPay is a managing console for handling all aspects of prepaid price lists and offers in telco industry. Currently is used by Fastweb, Telecom and other telco companies. It can handle logistic, billing, system, and customer (users,retailers and resellers) information.

Realisation of backend systems and web interfaces, RPC API to integrate customer's portals, and interfaces to systems controlling hardware to phone lines, and balance of accounts.

The architecture is based on opensource technologies such as WebWork, Tomcat, Hibernate, Spring IOC and AOP, with Java Language and Oracle database. The application is also supporting different servlet container (like resin, weblogic, etc) and databases (Postgresql was used in development, Oracle in test/integration/production environments).

Software Consultant at CSP - Torino, Ivrea, Milano Italy / Newbury, Reading, UK

CSP is a consultancy firm with offices in Torino, Milano (Italy) and Lugano (Switzerland), see: http://www.cspnet.it March 2004 - March 2004 (1 month)

Client: CSI Piemonte (Torino). Architecture of a Web Application for CSI Piemonte (Interreg ALPS). Web application development with proprietary web framework, and Oracle database. Integration with CSI (Common Service Infrastructure) proprietary communication framework, HTMPL (proprietary template engine), etc.

February 2004 - March 2004 (2 months)

Client: HP & Vodafone UK, on Ring Back Tone project. Architecture and development of a (prototype) "Vodafone Live!" WAP portal to "RingBack Tone" service, using Java, Struts, Resin. Integration with Vodafone 3PI Core Stack, PML markup language, ER Billing System, HP OpenCall, Widerthan Coloring.

January 2004 - February 2004 (2 months)

Client: CSI Piemonte (Torino), on project "Osservatorio Lavori Pubblici". Software development on applications, and proprietary frameworks (security, caching, and resource management).

December 2003 - December 2003

Client: Sun Microsystems, Vodafone Italy (Ivrea), on project "Download Server" (DoSe). Implemented a

platform for testing serialization compatibility between specific application APIs of Java components deployed different J2EE application servers thru RMI over IIOP on different Java VM. Used tools: JUnit, Ant, JUnitReport, EJB, IONA AppServer, JBoss, and proprietary component and interfaces.

October 2003 - November 2003 (2 months)

Client: Sun Microsystems, Vodafone Italy, on project "Java TestSuite Enhanced" (JTSE). Developer of a platform for test reservation and execution on J2ME wireless devices. Done with Struts, Sun ONE Studio & Application Server, EJB, J2ME OTA provisioning.

September 2003 - October 2003 (2 months)

Client: CSI Piemonte, on project "Flussi Turistici" (TURF). Development of a Swing application used by Turistic companies. Developed with Swing, Ant, XDoclet, EJBs, Oracle 8i, JBoss with Tomcat (Servlet, JSP, EJB), Swing and JavaWebStart on the client side.

Software Consultant at GFI OIS - Torino, Italy

GFI is an international consultancy firm based in France, GFI Italia, formerly known as GFI-OIS is derived by the fusion of GFI and OIS (Olivetti). See: http://www.gfitalia.it

February 2001 - August 2003 (2 years 7 months)

Client: CSI Piemonte. J2EE architect in the "Infrastrutture Applicative" team. Infrastructural and architectural design, mentoring on java based software development. Development and maintenance of proprietary frameworks and tools, technical writer. I've been involved in architecting and development of several J2EE application using JSP, Servlet, EJB, JDBC, XML (JBoss/WebLogic).

J2EE Lead Developer at Gruppo Banca Sella - Biella, Italy

Gruppo Banca Sella is a holding company controlling banks, financial services, insurances, leasing and credit. See: https://www.gruppobancasella.it

February 2000 - February 2001 (1 year 1 month)

Development of H2O (Host to Open) banking system, based on Java and J2EE technologies. RUP methodology, UML, XML and WebLogic 4.x. Last occupation as Team Leader.

Visual Basic Programmer at DM Group - Torino, Italy

April 1999 - February 2000 (11 months)

VisualBasic, MS Access VBA, Cobol NetExpress and Clipper developer using Oracle and SQL Server.

VAX/VMS & PC SysAdmin HelpDesk, Consultant at Gruppo DPS - Torino, Italy

May 1998 - March 1999 (11 months)

Client: SESAM SpA (now know as Atos Origin). Installation and configuration of networks and applications. Helpdesk on Compaq logistic applications running in VAX/VMS environment.

Cobol Programmer, Consultant at NewCom Data - Torino, Italy

January 1998 - May 1998 (5 months)

Client: San Paolo Bank (Torino). Software development, test and reporting in Cobol/CICS on DB2 database, using ROSCOE, TSO in IBM MVS environment.

Education

- High School Diploma on Computer Science, "ITIS G. PEANO" of Torino, 1991 1996
- Undergraduate in Computer Science Faculty "Dipartimento di Informatica" di Torino and "Ingegneria Informatica" at Politecnico di Torino, 1996 1998

Communities and Activities

Open source project architect an maintainer at OWNER API http://owner.aeonbits.org

- Bitcoin / Blockchain passionate and speaker, see: http://bitcoin.aeonbits.org
- Hobbyist photographer at http://www.luigiviggiano.photography/
- Java/Linux Technical Blogger since 2005: http://en.newinstance.it (currently offline)
- Founder of Java User Group Torino: http://www.jugtorino.it
- Member of The DZone Most Valued Blogger (MVB) Program: http://www.dzone.com/aboutmvb
- Premium Member of JGuru, top FAQ contributor: http://jguru.com/faq/contributors.jsp
- Member of Italian Agile Movement: http://www.agilemovement.it/profile/viggiano
- Speaker at Webb.it 2002 on seminary "SOAP: Simple Object Access Protocol"
- Speaker at Webb.it 2003 on seminary "J2EE Containers & Introduzione a JBoss"
- Speaker at Webb.it 2003 on seminary "Nuove funzionalita' del J2SE SDK 1.4"
- Speaker at Webb.it 2003 on seminary "Web Development J2EE: dettagli su Servlet & JSP"
- Speaker at Webb.it 2004 on seminary "Sviluppo WEB J2EE: Introduzione a Struts"
- Speaker at Webb.it 2004 on seminary "Sviluppo WEB J2EE: Struts hands-on"
- Technical Editor and Reviewer for the book "The Art of Java Web Development" by Neal Ford, 2004, Manning Publications Co.: http://www.manning.com/ford/
- LinkedIn profile: http://www.linkedin.com/in/viggiano
- StackOverflow: https://stackoverflow.com/users/258289/luigi-r-viggiano
- GitHub: https://github.com/lviggiano/

Interests

new technologies, open source, blockchain, bitcoin, artificial intelligence, robotics, renewable energy, crypto currencies, reading books, photography, gardening, movies, science fiction.